Young, Louisa mss., 1914-1919 LMC 2965
Lilly Library
Young, Louisa mss.
1914-1919
Lilly Library
Young, Frederick Charles
Young, Louisa
LMC 2965
2 Boxes
The Young, Louisa mss., 1914-1919, consist of World War I correspondence to Louisa (Louie) Young of Bath, England, primarily from her son, Private Fred C. Young, who served with the British Army in India and Mesopotamia.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchase: 2017
Arrangement
This collection maintains its received chronological order. Letters from correspondents other than Fred Young were separated and placed at the end of each year's series.
Biographical / Historical
Private Frederick Charles Young was born in Bath, England on October 21, 1895 to parents Charles and Louisa Young. During the First World War, he served with the Somerset Light Infantry in the 1st/4th Battalion Territorial Forces, which sailed from England to Madras, India (present-day Chennai) in October 1914. In January 1915 the battalion moved to Jullundur (Jalandhar) and then in August 1915 to Peshawar in response to uprisings in Afghanistan. In 1916 they moved to Mesopotamia, where Fred would spend the remainder of the war. Fred fought in the Battle of Sheikh Sa'ad against the Ottomans in January 1916 but otherwise served in an administrative capacity, clerking in the orderly room from mid-1916. On his 1915 and 1917 leaves, Fred visited his cousin Sydney, his wife Ellen, and their baby Elaine in Narayanganj, Eastern Bengal. The final letter in this collection is dated 26 February 1919.
Scope and Contents
The Young, Louisa mss., 1914-1919, consist of World War I correspondence saved by Louisa Young in a box decorated with marbled paper. The letters are addressed to Louisa (Louie) and her husband Charles (Charlie) at No. 1 Nelson Place in Bath before 1917 and at 8 Lower East Hayes after the family's move in 1917. The letters are primarily from her son, Private Fred C. Young, who served with the Somerset Light Infantry in the 1st/4th Battalion Territorial Forces, which was stationed in India and Mesopotamia. Additional correspondence is from Louisa Young's nephew, Frank Chappell, who served in the 59th Brigade, Royal Field Artillery; as well as from Louisa's nephew Sydney, who worked at a British firm in Narayanganj, Eastern Bengal.
Throughout the war, Fred writes a weekly letter home to his mother Louie, his father Charlie, and his siblings Marjorie and Stanley to let them know he is "A1" and "in the pink," that is, that he is alive and healthy. The letters describe a British soldier's daily life on the Indian and Mesopotamian fronts of the First World War. Letters include descriptions of the climate and surroundings, the various ailments of the troops, the health and wellbeing of Fred's friends Ralph, Godwin, Elgey, Pearson, and Allinson, thanks for parcels of chocolate, cigarettes, and socks sent from home, and the outcomes of sports matches played in camp. Nearly all the letters retain their original envelopes.
Note on Indexing Term - "Photography": Fred regularly sends home photographs purchased in camp of the Indian countryside and of "the natives." Most of the photographs are missing from the collection; however, written descriptions of the photographs exist in the letters. Surviving photographs are included with letters from 24 June 1915, 20 October 1915, and 4 July 1916. Note that these materials sometimes contain racist language.
Additional ephemera include a cinema schedule from 17 October 1917; a newspaper clipping on the difficulty of writing letters from 10 July 1918; and a program for the Basra & District Football League England versus Scotland match from 1 January 1919.
World War, 1914-1918; World War, 1914-1918 -- Campaigns -- Iraq; photography; India -- History -- British occupation, 1765-1947; Young, Frederick Charles; Chappell, Frank
- Box decorated with marbled paper in which the letters had been stored (Box 1)
- 1914 (Box 1)
  - Fred C. Young (Box 1)
    - September (Salisbury Plain) (Box 1)
    - October (en route to India) (Box 1)
    - November (Madras) (Box 1)
    - December (Madras) (Box 1)
  - Sydney and Ellen (Box 1)
  - Frank Chappell (Box 1)
  - Other correspondents (Box 1)
- 1915 (Box 1)
  - Fred C. Young (Box 1)
    - January-February (Jullundur) (Box 1)
    - March (Jullundur) (Box 1)
    - April (Jullundur) (Box 1)
    - May (Jullundur) (Box 1)
    - June (Jullundur) (Box 1)
    - July (Jullundur, Narayanganj) (Box 1)
    - August (Narayanganj, Jullundur, Peshawar) (Box 1)
    - September (Peshawar) (Box 1)
    - October (Peshawar) (Box 1)
    - November (Peshawar) (Box 1)
    - December (Peshawar) (Box 1)
  - Sydney and Ellen (Box 1)
  - Frank Chappell (Box 1)
  - Other correspondents (Box 1)
- 1916 (Box 1)
  - Fred C. Young (Box 1)
    - January (Peshawar, Nowshera) (Box 1)
    - February-March (Nowshera, Basra) (Box 1)
    - April-June (Basra) (Box 1)
    - July (Basra) (Box 1)
    - August (Basra) (Box 1)
    - September-October (Basra) (Box 1)
    - November (Basra) (Box 1)
    - December (Basra) (Box 1)
  - Ralph (Box 1)
  - Sydney and Ellen (Box 1)
  - Frank Chappell (Box 1)
  - Other correspondents (Box 1)
- 1917 (Box 2)
  - Fred C. Young (Box 2)
    - January (Basra) (Box 2)
    - February (Basra) (Box 2)
    - March (Basra) (Box 2)
    - April (Basra, Bombay) (Box 2)
    - May (Calcutta, Narayanganj) (Box 2)
    - June (Secunderabad) (Box 2)
    - July (Basra) (Box 2)
    - August (Basra) (Box 2)
    - September (Basra) (Box 2)
    - October (Basra) (Box 2)
    - November-December (Basra) (Box 2)
  - Frank Chappell (Box 2)
- 1918 (Box 2)
  - Fred C. Young (Box 2)
    - January (Basra) (Box 2)
    - February (Basra) (Box 2)
    - March (Basra) (Box 2)
    - April (Basra) (Box 2)
    - May (Basra) (Box 2)
    - June (Basra) (Box 2)
    - July (Basra) (Box 2)
    - August-September (Basra) (Box 2)
    - October (Basra) (Box 2)
    - November (Basra) (Box 2)
    - December (Basra) (Box 2)
  - Cpt. Allinson (Box 2)
  - Frank Chappell (Box 2)
- 1919 (Box 2)
  - Fred C. Young (Box 2)
    - January-February (Basra) (Box 2)
- No date (Box 2)
  - Fred C. Young (Box 2)